hey guys sh side welcome to concept and
coding and today in the first part of
spring boot security we will be
understanding its
architecture right but before we
start if you haven't gone through this
video kindly have a look because in this
one I have explained about different
type of attacks right csrf aises SQL
injection I have also explained about CS
so this will give you a better
understanding like why exactly we want
security okay so now I'm am assuming
that you already know about this attacks
now we need to protect our resources
from these attacks how we can do
that definitely we have to do
authentication and authorization
authentication means verify who you
are or in simple terms we can say that
how I would say that yes hey I am
shanen how I can tell I will provide my
username and password something and I
will tell somebody that yes this is me
so verify who you are authorization is
check what you are allowed to do so
maybe I am authenticated but I am only
allowed to
view but not allowed to update so that
is
the uh you can say that it's come under
the scope of authorization check what
only you are allowed to do even though
you are authenticated you are only
allowed to view the page you don't
allowed to update it or make any changes
okay so these two things has to be
properly handled in our application so
that we can protect our customers from
these
attempts and yeah that's where spring
boot security comes into the picture
very very
important and that's where we have to
first understand its architecture before
even we jump into different type of
authentication
also this is its architecture but here
if you
see it's just an extension of this one
filters so in video number 18 we have
already seen what are filters right and
where exactly they
fit so when the first request comes in
it goes to the subet container from
subet container to filter chain there
are multiple layers of filters filter 1
Filter 2 filter n okay and from this
filter it goes to a particular
dispatcher sulet and from dispatcher
sulet then Interceptor and then
Interceptor to actual the controller
where our
business logic lies or where our apis
are present so now Spring Security where
does it fit into this now if you are
already covered filters and you are
clear with the filter chain now whenever
you enable the Spring Security in your
application now here if you see there is
something called security filter chain
get added into your one of the filter
chain so you still have multiple filters
in your application filter 1 Filter 2
filter n but one of the filter get also
added which is security filter so
security filter is generally we can say
that security filter chain because there
are multiple security filters get
it okay consider it is like here
consider it like this filter chain here
you have filter 1 Filter 2 filter 3 like
this filter n consider this out of
filter three to this one this is your
security filter CH like these filters
are added because of security because
you opted for security and since you
opted for security these filters Will
Spring boot will add it okay in the
existing list of
filters okay so first thing is clear
right where exactly the security filter
chain fits it's just nothing but inside
whatever the filter chain you have it
just get fitted into that
only so there are are multiple filters
security filters okay now before I go
further like what are each of this
filter there are different
authentication method like form
based where you provide username
password you have like stateless one
like basic authentication
JWT
oo okay and there could be many
also so for each authentication method
for each authentication method there is
a different filter
involved okay so it's not so let's say
what I'm trying to say that maybe if you
are opting this authentication method
form
based then only these two are
eligible all are not
eligible okay let's say you wanted to go
with
JWT then it's may be these two let's say
there would be some another JWT filter
let's say these two username password
and these two only would be applicable
then this and this would not be
applicable similarly if you go with the
B basic authentication then this is not
applicable this is not applicable only
this is applicable so my point here to
tell you that depending upon which
authentication method you are choosing
which we will see later based on that
that particular filter is get processed
it's not like each request will go
through this then this then this then
this till end no okay so in if uh you
you are choosing basic authentication
then this will be skipped this will be
skipped only this will get
executed okay don't worry about each of
this filter as when we will do each and
every authentication method we will
understand its uh filter also okay but
for now try to understand the flow what
happens when the flow comes in now let's
say a request comes
in it goes to the filter and since you
are opted for security so will it goes
to one of the security filter also now
let's say it goes to one of the security
filter then what's the next step it will
pass
the request to authentication manager
now here if you see that in the
authentication manager except one
parameter which is of authenticate
object
authenticate so this authenticate object
is like contains multiple Fields again
this is not the right time to dig deeper
into each and every object we will see
when we will do each and every
authentication uh methods but for now
understand like very high level what is
the flow
architecture each authentication each
authenticate object contains like is
authenticated is
authenticated true
false okay so currently it's at this
point of time it is
false it's not authenticated what are
the
roles okay currently it would be let's
say empty I'm just saying so it is you
can say that this authenticate object
could be partial or incomplete at this
point of time and it is not user is not
authenticated so whenever the request
comes in yeah it will pass to the
filters and then it will pass through
the security filter chain and depending
upon the authentication method We are
following it will goes to one of the
filter and the filter will create this
authenticate object currently it would
be false it's not
authenticated it will pass that request
to authenticate manager authenticate
manager is an
interface and provider manager is the
implementation it's a default
implementation okay so what this
provider manager or you can say that
authentication manager does
this has the knowledge that my request
is coming from this
filter I have to pass it to which
provider which
provider okay so you can say that it's a
bridge between the filter and the
provider so this provider manager get a
request authenticate with the
authenticate object which is currently
partial it has the business logic which
knows that okay this is the filter
and this is the authentication method I
need to pass it to this provider and it
will delegate the authentication to one
of the provider there are multiple
providers it will delegate one of to the
one of the provider for example if you
are using username password or you can
say that session
based
session or session or you can say that
stateful authentication method then it
will pass the request to Dow
Authentication provider which takes care
of username password and also manage the
user
session similarly let's say if you are
uh following stateless and processing
JWT then this provider manager will
delegate the request to which JWT
authentication provider similarly if
you're following o it will pass to O we
will see that later when we will cover
each and every authentication method but
at least at this point of time we know
that okay if the request comes
filter chain one of the filter chain
will get invoked this will pass the
request to authentication manager
authentication manager implementation is
provider manager it's nothing but a
bridge between filter and one of the
provider which actual does the work or
actual does the
authentication okay for example this Dow
authentication provider like let's say
username password okay user provide the
username password so it actually does
the work so this password is you know
that the spring always store the
password in hash
form okay so now if whatever the
password is coming from user it has to
be encoded so it has proper integration
with password
encoder so raw password is Hash during
registration and during validation raw
password is hash and then only compared
so this only takes care of all the logic
now so it first do the hashing of the
password then it will fetch existing so
you are passing currently now a my
password is
XYZ but previously when you created it
you created XY let's say capital G so it
has to fed the existing details also
right so that will take care of it so it
also has integration with user details
service again it's an
interface user Detail Service has two
flavor in memory and jdbc user detail
manager in memory means all this
username password is stored in
memory okay so it's you can say that
it's a
temporary but if you want to store it in
the DB you can use jdbc user detail
manager where the username password is
stored in the DB so it will load it and
it will do comparison whatever user is
now sending us and whatever we have
received earlier are they matching or
not based on that it will again return
back with the authenticate object only
but now it will be complete
authenticate true
false okay and ultimately authentication
manager return back to the filter with
the fully authenticated response whether
it is authenticated yes or no and this
filter
if it authenticated it will store the
object into security
context if authentication is false it
will throw bad
credentials but if it is fully
authenticated like yes it this user is
authenticated true this one of the
filter which uh which was invoked it
stores that authenticate object into
security
context
now this security context will get added
into your request goes into the
dispatcher
subet if you have the Interceptor it
will go through the Interceptor and
ultimately it will reach to the
controller your API so at this point of
time your API also has this
security context
one more thing I just want to highlight
again since we have multiple
authentication method like form based
like basic
authentication
JWT
oo considered this architecture as a
template
today okay because for each
authentication method we will
again draw this architecture but for
each flow there would be some minor
changes okay just for example for form
based
login
okay you are doing certain extra steps
here but let's say for basic
authentication you are totally missing
this step you don't need this step you
don't need to put it so I'm just giving
you one example okay we will I don't
want to jump into each authentication
method what we are doing what we are not
doing but I'm just giving you one
example that maybe depending upon each
authentication method we might be doing
one of the step or we might be skipping
or doing extra in this architecture
itself so consider this architecture as
a base and for each authentication
method we will run through this base
template or architecture itself okay
which filter get invoked which filter
get es skipped why and which filter got
invoked from this filter what exactly
happened in the authenticate object
which provider got invoked what that
provider du does actually inside okay
what's the response or fully
authenticate object looks like okay and
what else data we put into security
context and what
exactly the controller uses it
like okay so we will connect the dots
for each authenticated method later but
for now just understand this is a flow
when any request comes in and have you
have integrated the spring spring boot
security in your application okay so in
a spring boot in your spring boot
project if your project is already
present which we are already this
playlist is all going so I think by this
time you already have set up the spring
boot project so you need to add the
below
dependencies okay so these two
dependency you can add one is spring
boot starter security so this spring
boot security uh dependency is like add
feature like authentication
authorization and the filter so this
filter chain will get included this all
filter chain this authentication manager
provider everything get
included and there is something called
Spring session jdbc this this is only
required this is optional it's not
mandatory this is only required if you
want to maintain session based
authentication and you want to store
into the DB if you want to store into
the ultimately
DB then you need it but we will see that
when we will actually do uh
stateful stateful authentication so for
now you can you can say that you don't
need it you only need this
one but if you're setting up a new
project in the spring initializer itself
you can set up Spring web and you can
take Spring Security so with the Spring
Security you will get
this
okay and only if you want DB support uh
for the session B you can take it but
again this is for now not required we
will see when we will do state state
full
authentication okay now now we will go
ahead with each and every authentication
method in depth considering this as a
base architecture guys thank you bye